A Guide to the Papers of Thomas A. Compton, 1825-1847
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas A. Compton 1825-1847
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-116
This collection consists of 24 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a deposit of Mrs. J. B. Patterson of Fishersville VA in February 1932.
Biographical/Historical Information
Represented in the collection are Thomas A. Compton, originally of Culpeper County, Va., later merchant in Mississippi; his parents, Walter and Elizabeth Compton, and his sister, Henrietta Compton Burkly, originally of Culpeper County, Va., later of Carroll County, Tenn.; and Burwell K. Wood, merchant, of Culpeper County and Gaines Crossroads (later Gainesville), Va.
Scope and Content
The papers include family correspondence, 1825-1840, to Thomas A. Compton, chiefly from Walter and Elizabeth Compton, Henrietta Compton Burkly, and Burwell K. Wood, concerning news of friends and family in Virginia and Tennessee, teaching school in Tennessee, religion, a legal suit (Walter Compton v. Bird Eastham), an offer to sell slaves for land and slave hiring, emigration from Virginia, the poverty of the land in Virginia, observations on national and state politics, and courtship.
The papers also include list, 1846, of personal property and slaves of Mrs. Margaret Shaw's estate (Mississippi); letter, 17 February 1847, asking the correspondent to help slaves cross a river in Mississippi.
Contents List
- Misc. Letters to Thomas A Compton, 1825 - 1840
  - Bird Eastham, writing from Tennessee, discusses teaching school, prospects for school in Mississippi, an anecdote of General Lafayette, and family news. 1825 May 20 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Bird Eastham writes in affirmation of friendship, a visit to New Orleans, teaching school, and family news. 1826 Dec 20 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Alexander Sandford, writing from Fort McHenry, mentions the recent loss of his wife, and the assignment of his son as an Indian agent. 1828 Jan 11 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - John Monison, a nephew, writes from Gaines Crossroads to report family news (sicknesses and death). 1840 MAY 30 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Family Letters to Thomas A. Compton, 1825 - 1833
  - Henrietta A. Compton, a sister, writes from Culpeper VA with family news and plans to relocate. She discusses religion, mentioning Methodist circuit preachers. 1825 MAR 22 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Henrietta A. Compton writes about family news and illnesses, religion, health, and local marriages. 1825 JUL 8 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Walter Compton, Culpeper, Va., writes to his son in reference to his litigation with Bird Eastham. He prefaces the letter with the deposition of Richard H. Field, also of Culpeper. 1825 DEC 24 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Walter Compton writes concerning legal matters, debts, family news, and his wish to emigrate. 1826 AUG 7 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Henrietta A. Compton writes about family news, her friend, marriages, death, and religion. 1826 SEP 22 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Walter Compton and Elizabeth Compton, writing separately, discuss family news, an offer to sell slaves for land, and mention opposition to Henrietta's marriage. 1826 DEC 15 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Walter Compton writes from Carroll County, Tennessee, describing the rigors of the journey and news relating to relocation and lack of funds. 1829 MAR 8 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Elizabeth Compton writes re: family news, land and debt. 1831 AUG 25 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Elizabeth Compton reports that she has managed to purchase land with assistance from Col. Anderson, and explains her present situation and the difficulties she has experienced. 1831 DEC 3 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Grace Ann Compton, Henry City, Tenn., writes to her brother concerning the debt owed William Berkley and the threat of legal action by John Gibbs to collect from her what Berkley owes him. She is hiring out a slave, Rachel, for a year in order to pay the debt, but she doesn't expect to be granted a delay. Family news includes report of her father having taken the money Thomas gave to his mother, which "is now in the hands of some of the Hankins." Other subjects mentioned include illness and her hope to be married. 1833 JUL 28 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Thomas Compton, an uncle, writes concerning family news and "your friend Mr. Bayly" who is traveling in Virginia and his aid to [Thomas' son] Telghman in Front Royal, Va. He notes that his son "has been spending his time very unprofitably at home with me" and he will accept the offer to "send him on to your guidance and patronage." 1833 SEP 3 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Letters from Burwell K. Wood, Gaines Crossroads, Va.
  - Writing from Culpeper County, Va., Burwell notes the good news of Thomas' recovery [from an illness] and prosperity, contrasted with the state of business / farming locally. He expresses a desire to emigrate, noting that William Morrison and his family, plus others, will move to Tennessee. A number of illnesses and deaths are mentioned, plus a few marriages. 1826 OCT 18 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Besides news of illnesses, deaths, and courtships, Burwell notes that "Brother John & myself have sold our stock of goods at Flint Hill and expected to have sold out my interest in the store at the Cross Road to Mr. Deathuage, but we could not agree, at this time." 1827 JUN 9 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Burwell expresses "joy" to hear from Thomas and his "comfortable circumstances" (in Mississippi) and writes of family news and the poverty of business in Virginia and resulting financial difficulties. 1827 AUG 6 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Burwell notes the emigration from Virginia, and reiterates his desire and that of his brother, John, to relocate to the South. (According to what Thomas' brother, Walter, had told him earlier in the day, even his father is moving to Tennessee). The letter includes news that William Morrison has purchased land in Tennessee, as well as family and business news. The commentary on government and politics reveals that Burwell favors Andrew Jackson. 1828 APR 27 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Burwell reports that he, his brother John, and Mr. Deathuage plan to leave Virginia "next fall." He includes the news that Thomas' father and family has "set out for the western district in Tennessee" in company with William Berkly and his family. In frankly discussing his desire to move to a healthier economic climate, Burwell states, "There is no country that I would prefer to Virginia for health and society, but the current of the times seems to be against her...." He also laments that he remains a bachelor. 1828 NOV 29 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Burwell reports that business has greatly improved for him and Mr. Deathuage, although many farmers, such as "old John Miller," had to sell grain at depressed prices. Burwell reports on family news and continued emigration, and notes that the "property at Gaines Crossroads has been sold by Ficklin & Warren to William Fletcher..." He and Mr. Deathuage wish to purchase the property, but understand the title is clouded by the case of "John Morrison's Creditors vs. The United States" (now in the Supreme Court). Burwell comments on politics and the amendment of the [Virginia] constitution. 1829 JUN 25 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Burwell is uncertain of the division of the estate of John Fletcher between William Fletcher and John Hopper. Business continues poorly, and he is anxious to hear from Thomas' father. He mentions politics and the amendment of the [Virginia] constitution, that he has a prospect for marriage, and that he looks forward to Thomas' visit to Virginia. 1830 MAR 12 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Legal Papers
  - "A Schedule of the Personal Property of the Estate of the late Mrs. Margaret Shaw." Recorded in Jefferson County, Mississippi, the list includes slaves. 1846 JUL 23 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Unsigned letter, Jefferson County, Mississippi to Mr. Bagnell, instructing him to help Negroes cross "Big Black" [river]. Inventory of personal property on verso. 1847 FEB 17 (Box-folder 1:4)